<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-12T19:15:57+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">honest2davis</title><subtitle>I make beats for artists to help share their story</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Three excuses to overcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three excuses to overcome" /><published>2020-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-its-a-saturated-market-no-one-will-listen-to-your-music&quot;&gt;1. It’s a saturated market, no one will listen to your music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been building my experience in the music industry for a number of years and I help artists and creators by selling them &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundee.com/honest2davis&quot;&gt;instrumentals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. How is this possible? Because the market is getting bigger. In 2015, the IFPI measured the music market to have received $15 billion USD in revenue. Fast forward to 2019 and it’s valued at $19 billion USD &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ifpi.org/media/downloads/GMR2019-en.pdf&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This growth makes it &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like it’s a saturated market but in actual fact, it’s just that artists can reach audiences a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;when-it-comes-to-a-saturated-market-think-of-your-music-as-a-coffee-shop-its-a-saturated-market-for-sure-but-the-different-experiences-processes-and-accessibility-of-your-coffee-shop-gives-you-as-an-artist-a-chance-to-reach-an-audience&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When it comes to a saturated market, think of your music as a coffee shop. It’s a saturated market for sure but the different experiences, processes and accessibility of your &lt;em&gt;coffee shop&lt;/em&gt; gives you as an artist a chance to reach an audience.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-no-one-will-buy-your-music&quot;&gt;2. No one will buy your music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is technically &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; because physical sales of music has been on the decline since 2005. We have technology to make it easier to listen to music. Technology has allowed music to become available anywhere at any time on any device. If massive companies like Apple, Google and Amazon have their own streaming platforms - it validates that they see a financial opportunity through this model as opposed to physical sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;whilst-theres-an-increasingly-low-chance-of-people-buying-your-music-theres-a-higher-chance-of-people-buying-your-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whilst there’s an increasingly low chance of people buying your music, there’s a higher chance of people buying your &lt;em&gt;“experience”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; changes the approach with how we can monetise the music journey. The old way was to buy some studio time, record and then spend money on distribution and then more money marketing. The new way (if it’s independant or major/minor label placements) is continuing to grow. Technology is making it easier for artists and audiences to interact together to sell different experiences. Merchandise, affiliate schemes, collaborations - all different ways to create an experience that goes beyond music that entices audiences to spend money on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-its-not-a-stable-career-path&quot;&gt;3. It’s not a stable career path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in Australia - one of the most stable careers you could’ve had was in aviation. Covid-19 has decimated this industry and made people question the deifnition of ‘stable’. In 2008, Kevin Kelly wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;https://kk.org/thetechnium/1000-true-fans/&quot;&gt;essay&lt;/a&gt; (before they called them ‘blogs’) on a theory that if you could get 1,000 fans on average to spend $100 on your musicianship in a year, that’s $100,000 you could make as a salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that you would get $100 per fan has a few models of how you can make this happen and &lt;a href=&quot;https://indiebandalliance.com/&quot;&gt;Indie Balance&lt;/a&gt; have written more around this too. I have the ebook if you’d like it which goes through three simple steps to earn as a musician full time. Just send me your email so that I can send you the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;form method=&quot;POST&quot; action=&quot;https://api.slapform.com/beats@honest2davis.com&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;name&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;name&quot; id=&quot;name&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;email&quot;&gt;Email&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;slap_replyto&quot; id=&quot;email&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_replyto will set the reply-to as the submitter's email! --&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;ul class=&quot;actions&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Get the e-book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;slap_redirect&quot; value=&quot;http://localhost:4000/thank-you&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_redirect allows you to set a custom redirect/thank you page --&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">As you get into making and releasing music, you'll come up against these common excuses. The reason why they're common because there isn’t much knowledge around the business mechanics of music.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/billboard.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/billboard.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rap Fundamentals Pt 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rap Fundamentals Pt 1" /><published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-wrong-with-my-raps&quot;&gt;What’s wrong with my raps?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You start as a fan of the craft with access to a whole bunch of incredible rappers slaying the mic both past and present. Vivid imagery of MJ on the stage when Drake’s referring to the black leather glove no sequins. The repetitive I GOT I GOT I GOT before the beat drops to Kendrick Lamar’s track loyalty. Even that little adlib at the beginning of The Box by Roddy Rich just sits in the track so nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it’s your turn…so far you’ve got the cat who sat on the mat pull out my AK-blap blap with the hoes and the diamonds on my chain..Don’t know how but it just doesn’t seems like you’ve got the Midas touch when it comes to crafting you’re raps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then you listen to your favourite artist again and you try find more inventive ways to get baguette diamonds on that custom Virgil Patek watch and again, the raps just don’t seem to fit. Might as well quit right? You could, or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;check-your-influences&quot;&gt;Check your influences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sound will be influenced by the artist you listen to which is great, you just need to pay attention to what it ‘is’ that you like about them. The flow, the metaphors, the melodies all of the things take a note of these and then step back from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{image] 
 take a note of these and then step back from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common theme that all these rappers are able to do is tell a story in a structured manner that you relate to. Yeah you might not be in the trap slinging crack, but you might be at uni struggling to get those grades. You might not be out here with the big booty bitches but that might be the struggle - you ain’t getting no big booty!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, looking at your favourite artists, they tell stories that you relate to and trigger a way that you feel. You don’t have to use their words and their experiences but you can do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-listener&quot;&gt;The listener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is to show that what makes good music is having a group of people who listen to it. The people who listen to it relate to your music and ultimately enjoy it. Stepping back from this, people are listening to your music. So you need to structure raps that people would want to listen to. Sound airy fairy but I’ll get to the main point in a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key rules that you can follow to immediately get things moving in the right direction. These are basic guides to follow because you should be able to extend on these as you improve on your craft. If you’re laughing and find this a waste of time, maybe buy a beat from my catalogue and get some raps over it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pov-in-the-non-pornhub-sense&quot;&gt;POV (in the non pornhub sense)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok now that your mind is out of the gutter, the first basic frame is that you need to establish where you’re rapping from. Are you rapping through your eyes or the eyes of someone else? A rap example of this is Roddy Rich - Ballin’ have a listen to his story about himself and the people around him. Get on Genius and follow along with the lyrics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YS0h2-hy9rw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of a song with two different POV’s by the same songwriter (sorry it aint a rap one, but it’s been sampled enough) is the Pina Colada Song. The song is about a guy doing a 1980’s tinder swipe via the classifieds in the paper and someone responds. Spoiler: the person who responds is his wife. If you want a song with two people in opposite POV’s - Chris Brown and Lil’ Dicky is the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TazHNpt6OTo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tense&quot;&gt;The tense&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple. The past, the present the future. Or a mixture of all of these. If you’re rapping about something right now or yesterday or something in the future. Guide your listener from the POV and where you’re coming from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good example of past tense is Ahmad - Back in the Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/q0WMSovOboY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a listen to Ice Cube’s past tense from his POV for It Was A Good Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h4UqMyldS7Q?start=11&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll update the next blog piece because we’re going to cover subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;honest2davis&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">This three part series looks into rap theory given all the books written on this subject are based around songwriting which is the same thing but pretty boring to read.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/pic-10.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/pic-10.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>