<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-05T04:24:47+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">honest2davis</title><subtitle>I make beats for artists to help share their story</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Six Places to Find Free Beats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/six-places-to-find-free-beats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Six Places to Find Free Beats" /><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/six-places-to-find-free-beats</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/six-places-to-find-free-beats/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;six-places-to-find-free-beats&quot;&gt;“Six Places to Find Free Beats”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you even consider buying beats, you’ve got to know where you can find free beats to download. There are many sites and beat makers (myself included) who are helping artist by creating free beats to download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little difficult when you search for beats online and you end up looking at the different Beats By Dre headphones when you’re looking for hip hop and rap instrumentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put together six places you can find free beats to download and also some notes to take into consideration when you find ways to download beats from the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/youtube.png&quot; alt=&quot;youtube&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-youtube&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtube.com/&quot;&gt;1. YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to finding free beats, YouTube should be your first stop for two reasons. It’s accessible on mobile, web or app and secondly, the search engine can help give you a continuous stream of beats. Why? This is because YouTube has 2 billion logged in users per month, so they work hard to ensure they’re serving you with relevant results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to get started is to search term search a ’type beat’ of your favourite artist. For example ‘drake type beat 2020’ and the top beats are relevant ones others have used so it’s a relatively tried and true method to find beats that you might like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protip:&lt;/strong&gt; add an ‘x’ after the artists names to find combinations of type beats people are looking for. Eg, ‘drake x’ bring up a ‘drake x Bryson tiller type beat’ which might of interest to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/soundcloud.png&quot; alt=&quot;soundcloud&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-soundcloud&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundcloud.com/&quot;&gt;2. SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it’s been meme’d with the likes of Lil Pump and the term soundcloud rapper (url), SoundCloud is still a place to find free beats to download as well as beat makers and producers who are creating a sound that might help to expand your listening horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before marketplaces and YouTube were making it easier for you to listen to beats, Soundcloud was one of the few places to specialise as a place for musicians to upload their tracks. Soundcloud as a platform helped us to find some prominent artist like XXXTentacion, Post Malone, Juice WRLD, 21 Savage, Chance The Rapper. Interesting to note that each of these artist have had a top 5 billboard song too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/instagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;instagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://instagram.com/&quot;&gt;3. Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instagram is another massive platform which is a must when on the search for free beats. The difference between the other two is that you need to use hashtags to find free beats that you might be interested. What makes Instagram a great source is that a wave of younger producers are on Instagram and sharing both their finished beats as well as some of the beats that they’re working on. The messaging in instagram makes it easier to develop relationships with beat makers and give you a chance to build something together. I collab all the time via insta so it’s a good avenue to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/marketplace.png&quot; alt=&quot;soundee&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-online-marketplaces&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundee.com/honest2davis&quot;&gt;4. Online marketplaces&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://beatstars.com/&quot;&gt;Beatstars&lt;/a&gt; is a marketplace that allows music producers to sell beats and give away free beats. There are similar platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;http://airbit.com/&quot;&gt;Airbit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tracktrain.com/&quot;&gt;Tracktrain&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundee.com/&quot;&gt;Soundee&lt;/a&gt; that provide these services as well. I like the fact that they’re easy to use and it’s a fair exchange to producers in the game. However it’s not as easy to navigate if you’re unsure of what you’re specifically looking. I use soundee if you’re interested and if you need some questions answered around how my licensing structure works, you can find it on my &lt;a href=&quot;/faq&quot;&gt;FAQ page&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/twitter.png&quot; alt=&quot;twitter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/honest2davis&quot;&gt;5. Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a two way channel I’ve found to be successful for artists looking to buy and download free beats. Firstly, you can do the hashtag research to find types of beats similar to Instagram, but the other thing you can do is put out tweets asking people to send beats. Check this twitter search term for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=send%20beats&amp;amp;src=typed_query&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;send beats&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and you’ll see what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/honest2davis.png&quot; alt=&quot;honest2davis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-your-friendly-local-organic-free-producer---me&quot;&gt;6. Your friendly local, organic free producer - me!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you’re reading this, I’m hoping it’s because you downloaded my pack of five free beats (free.honest2davis.com) and that some of my other beats might be of interest to you. It’s not an easy maze to navigate so feel free to check out my beat store and check out some of my beats. There’s something there for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">Before you even consider buying beats, you’ve got to know where you can find free beats to download.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/pic10.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/pic10.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Free Beats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/free-beats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Free Beats" /><published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/free-beats</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/free-beats/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;need-a-freebie&quot;&gt;Need a freebie?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah it’s a little tough out there so let me help you with a 5 pack of free beats with the contract in them so that you can use them commercially too. Pop your email down in the form below and I’ll send you the link directly for some free beats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;form method=&quot;POST&quot; action=&quot;https://api.slapform.com/beats@honest2davis.com&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;name&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;name&quot; id=&quot;name&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;email&quot;&gt;Email&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;slap_replyto&quot; id=&quot;email&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_replyto will set the reply-to as the submitter's email! --&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;ul class=&quot;actions&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Get Free Beat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;slap_redirect&quot; value=&quot;http://localhost:4000/thank-you&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_redirect allows you to set a custom redirect/thank you page --&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">Let's keep it simple, can I help you with some free beats?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/pic07.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/pic07.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Tips on Buying Beats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/get-started/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Tips on Buying Beats" /><published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/get-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/get-started/">&lt;!-- 
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/promotion/getting-started.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &quot;Buying beats is an exciting step in your career as an artist. It's more than just a matter of 'buying beats', it represents that you're taking your craft serious and that you're evolving. Given you're looking to spend your hard earned cash, I wanted to share some information with to help you when you buy beats. There's a lot of 'noise' in this space so hopefully this helps.&quot;
&lt;/p&gt; 
--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-mp3s-for-beginners-and-wavs-for-advanced&quot;&gt;1. MP3’s for beginners and WAV’s for advanced.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my beats follow a typical song structure of three verses and three hook sections. If you’re just starting out - I recommend getting the MP3 and letting the track guide you. If you want more control of the end product, advanced artists should look to get the WAV files which also include all the track outs. If it helps, you can &lt;strong&gt;buy 1 and get 2 free&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;check-out-the-beat-store-below&quot;&gt;Check out the beat store below:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&quot;soundee_player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://soundee.com/player/1426?iframe=1&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:600px;max-width:980px;&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-buy-what-you-can-afford&quot;&gt;2. Buy what you can afford&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re in a pandemic which is creating uncertain times. Prioritise your health before buying beats. I’ve included bulk deals to help make it easier on the wallet. If you’re feeling a beat and it’s out of the price range, free to get in contact to make an offer on any beat you have your eye on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-dont-be-afraid-to-ask&quot;&gt;3. Don’t be afraid to ask!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not ready to buy something right now, &lt;strong&gt;pop your email down below&lt;/strong&gt; so I can give you a five pack of royalty free beats! Hope that can help the journey. Happy to help you where I can. I’ve also got more information on the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; that have loads of articles to help you with your music journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;form method=&quot;POST&quot; action=&quot;https://api.slapform.com/beats@honest2davis.com&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;name&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;name&quot; id=&quot;name&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;email&quot;&gt;Email&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;slap_replyto&quot; id=&quot;email&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_replyto will set the reply-to as the submitter's email! --&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;ul class=&quot;actions&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Get Free Beat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;slap_redirect&quot; value=&quot;http://localhost:4000/thank-you&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_redirect allows you to set a custom redirect/thank you page --&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">Buying beats is an exciting step in your career as an artist. It's more than just a matter of 'buying beats', it represents that you're taking your craft serious and that you're evolving. Given you're looking to spend your hard earned cash, I wanted to share some information with to help you when you buy beats. There's a lot of 'noise' in this space so hopefully this helps.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/promotion/getting-started.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/promotion/getting-started.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Three excuses to overcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three excuses to overcome" /><published>2020-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-its-a-saturated-market-no-one-will-listen-to-your-music&quot;&gt;1. It’s a saturated market, no one will listen to your music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been building my experience in the music industry for a number of years and I help artists and creators by selling them &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundee.com/honest2davis&quot;&gt;instrumentals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. How is this possible? Because the market is getting bigger. In 2015, the IFPI measured the music market to have received $15 billion USD in revenue. Fast forward to 2019 and it’s valued at $19 billion USD &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ifpi.org/media/downloads/GMR2019-en.pdf&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This growth makes it &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like it’s a saturated market but in actual fact, it’s just that artists can reach audiences a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;when-it-comes-to-a-saturated-market-think-of-your-music-as-a-coffee-shop-its-a-saturated-market-for-sure-but-the-different-experiences-processes-and-accessibility-of-your-coffee-shop-gives-you-as-an-artist-a-chance-to-reach-an-audience&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When it comes to a saturated market, think of your music as a coffee shop. It’s a saturated market for sure but the different experiences, processes and accessibility of your &lt;em&gt;coffee shop&lt;/em&gt; gives you as an artist a chance to reach an audience.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-no-one-will-buy-your-music&quot;&gt;2. No one will buy your music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is technically &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; because physical sales of music has been on the decline since 2005. We have technology to make it easier to listen to music. Technology has allowed music to become available anywhere at any time on any device. If massive companies like Apple, Google and Amazon have their own streaming platforms - it validates that they see a financial opportunity through this model as opposed to physical sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;whilst-theres-an-increasingly-low-chance-of-people-buying-your-music-theres-a-higher-chance-of-people-buying-your-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whilst there’s an increasingly low chance of people buying your music, there’s a higher chance of people buying your &lt;em&gt;“experience”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; changes the approach with how we can monetise the music journey. The old way was to buy some studio time, record and then spend money on distribution and then more money marketing. The new way (if it’s independant or major/minor label placements) is continuing to grow. Technology is making it easier for artists and audiences to interact together to sell different experiences. Merchandise, affiliate schemes, collaborations - all different ways to create an experience that goes beyond music that entices audiences to spend money on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-its-not-a-stable-career-path&quot;&gt;3. It’s not a stable career path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in Australia - one of the most stable careers you could’ve had was in aviation. Covid-19 has decimated this industry and made people question the deifnition of ‘stable’. In 2008, Kevin Kelly wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;https://kk.org/thetechnium/1000-true-fans/&quot;&gt;essay&lt;/a&gt; (before they called them ‘blogs’) on a theory that if you could get 1,000 fans on average to spend $100 on your musicianship in a year, that’s $100,000 you could make as a salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that you would get $100 per fan has a few models of how you can make this happen and &lt;a href=&quot;https://indiebandalliance.com/&quot;&gt;Indie Balance&lt;/a&gt; have written more around this too. I have the ebook if you’d like it which goes through three simple steps to earn as a musician full time. Just send me your email so that I can send you the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;form method=&quot;POST&quot; action=&quot;https://api.slapform.com/beats@honest2davis.com&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;name&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;name&quot; id=&quot;name&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;field&quot;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&quot;email&quot;&gt;Email&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;slap_replyto&quot; id=&quot;email&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_replyto will set the reply-to as the submitter's email! --&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;ul class=&quot;actions&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Get the e-book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;slap_redirect&quot; value=&quot;http://localhost:4000/thank-you&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- slap_redirect allows you to set a custom redirect/thank you page --&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">As you get into making and releasing music, you'll come up against these common excuses. The reason why they're common because there isn’t much knowledge around the business mechanics of music.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/three-excuses-to-overcome.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rap Fundamentals Pt 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rap Fundamentals Pt 1" /><published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/rap-fundamentals-pt-1/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-wrong-with-my-raps&quot;&gt;What’s wrong with my raps?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You start as a fan of the craft with access to a whole bunch of incredible rappers slaying the mic both past and present. Vivid imagery of MJ on the stage when Drake’s referring to the black leather glove no sequins. The repetitive I GOT I GOT I GOT before the beat drops to Kendrick Lamar’s track loyalty. Even that little adlib at the beginning of The Box by Roddy Rich just sits in the track so nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it’s your turn…so far you’ve got the cat who sat on the mat pull out my AK-blap blap with the hoes and the diamonds on my chain..Don’t know how but it just doesn’t seems like you’ve got the Midas touch when it comes to crafting you’re raps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then you listen to your favourite artist again and you try find more inventive ways to get baguette diamonds on that custom Virgil Patek watch and again, the raps just don’t seem to fit. Might as well quit right? You could, or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;check-your-influences&quot;&gt;Check your influences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sound will be influenced by the artist you listen to which is great, you just need to pay attention to what it ‘is’ that you like about them. The flow, the metaphors, the melodies all of the things take a note of these and then step back from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{image] 
 take a note of these and then step back from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common theme that all these rappers are able to do is tell a story in a structured manner that you relate to. Yeah you might not be in the trap slinging crack, but you might be at uni struggling to get those grades. You might not be out here with the big booty bitches but that might be the struggle - you ain’t getting no big booty!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, looking at your favourite artists, they tell stories that you relate to and trigger a way that you feel. You don’t have to use their words and their experiences but you can do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-listener&quot;&gt;The listener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is to show that what makes good music is having a group of people who listen to it. The people who listen to it relate to your music and ultimately enjoy it. Stepping back from this, people are listening to your music. So you need to structure raps that people would want to listen to. Sound airy fairy but I’ll get to the main point in a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key rules that you can follow to immediately get things moving in the right direction. These are basic guides to follow because you should be able to extend on these as you improve on your craft. If you’re laughing and find this a waste of time, maybe buy a beat from my catalogue and get some raps over it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pov-in-the-non-pornhub-sense&quot;&gt;POV (in the non pornhub sense)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok now that your mind is out of the gutter, the first basic frame is that you need to establish where you’re rapping from. Are you rapping through your eyes or the eyes of someone else? A rap example of this is Roddy Rich - Ballin’ have a listen to his story about himself and the people around him. Get on Genius and follow along with the lyrics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YS0h2-hy9rw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of a song with two different POV’s by the same songwriter (sorry it aint a rap one, but it’s been sampled enough) is the Pina Colada Song. The song is about a guy doing a 1980’s tinder swipe via the classifieds in the paper and someone responds. Spoiler: the person who responds is his wife. If you want a song with two people in opposite POV’s - Chris Brown and Lil’ Dicky is the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TazHNpt6OTo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tense&quot;&gt;The tense&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple. The past, the present the future. Or a mixture of all of these. If you’re rapping about something right now or yesterday or something in the future. Guide your listener from the POV and where you’re coming from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good example of past tense is Ahmad - Back in the Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/q0WMSovOboY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a listen to Ice Cube’s past tense from his POV for It Was A Good Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h4UqMyldS7Q?start=11&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll update the next blog piece because we’re going to cover subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;honest2davis&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>honest2davis</name></author><summary type="html">This three part series looks into rap theory given all the books written on this subject are based around songwriting which is the same thing but pretty boring to read.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/pic-10.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/blog/pic-10.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>